好的，嗯。让我们开始吧。
Okay, yeah. Let's get started.
好的好的，谢谢你们的到来。
Cool, cool. Thanks for coming.
我们将继续讨论一些基础内容。
And we are going to continue to talk about some basics.
好的，在那之前，我想先说一下关于注册的最新情况。
Okay. Before that, I want to give some update on enrollment.
我觉得有几个学生退课了。
So I think a few students drop.
所以我们还有60个空位。
So we have 60 more seats.
我会和CSE合作，安排下一个本科生的注册。
I'm going to work with CSE to enroll the next bachelor students.
然后在周四，可能是在讲座之后，
Then on Thursday, probably after lecture,
我会再次和CSE一起处理相关事宜。
I'm going to work with CSE again.
我相信到时候有些学生交了作业后，会选择退课。
I believe at that time after some students homework, they are going to drop the scores,
所以会有更多的座位。
so there will be more seats.
这也意味着我们周四很可能会有作业一准备好。
Which also means that Thursday likely we'll have our homework one ready.
好的，那我们今天开始讲内容吧。
Yeah. Okay, let's get started with the content today.
还记得我们上周学了什么吗？有三点，对吧？
So so still remember what we learned last week, right? Three things, right?
第一，我们做了一个非常非常快速的机器学习回顾，
The first one is we took a very, very fast review of machine learning,
尤其是当今的机器学习。
especially today's machine learning.
我们把我们的工作内容总结为
We summarize our workload as
Metham加上softmax再加上一些其他算子，从计算的角度来看，对吧？
Metham plus softmax plus a few other operators, right, from the computational perspective, okay?
然后我们开始定义计算图，嗯，还记得
And we start defining the computational graphs, um, still remember
节点和边的定义吗？
the definitions of nodes and edges, right?
所以节点代表计算操作符和它的潜力，边基本上就是
So nodes represent the computational operators and its a potential, and edges are basically
数据流动的方向和依赖关系。
the data flowing directions and dependency.
然后我们开始讨论，特别是 TensorFlow 和 PyTorch 的编程风格，
And then we start talking about the programming flavors of especially TenerfornPatrig,
我们发现它们非常不同。
and we find that they are quite different.
一个是符号式的，另一个是命令式的。
One is symbolic, the other is imperative.
我们开始讨论静态和动态，对吧？
We start talking about static and dynamic, right?
我们还谈到了最新的技术，叫做
And we also talk about the latest technique which is called
JIT，即时编译，以及它们如何在一定程度上解决这个问题。
JIT just in time compilation and how they can basically solve this problem a little bit.
好的。我们来做一些选择题，非常简单。
Okay. Let's do some MCQ. Very easy.
你是一家为用户提供积分的公司的机器学习工程师，
So you are machine learning engineer at a company that is providing points to users,
你的目标是为这些Ms实现高效的推理。例如，你是OpenA，你得到了
your goal is running efficient inference for these Ms. For example, you are open A and you are given
一个同时拥有符号和Impervid API的框架，
a framework which has both symbolic and impervid API,
这在今天的Interf和Petrox中都成立。
which is true for both Interf and Petrox today.
在设计你的系统时，
While designing your system,
我将给你四个选项。
I'm going to give you four options.
看看这个，选哪一个？
Take a look at that. Which one?
哪一个？B，对吧？
Which one? B, right?
很简单，因为你希望在开发阶段更容易调试。
Pretty simple, yeah, because you want something that's easier to debug at development.
一旦你理清了你的程序，基本上就可以用性能最高的方式部署它。
And once you figure out your program, you basically deploy it using the most high performance one.
好，第二个问题。
Okay? Second one.
以下哪项关于数据流图是不正确的，看看AB、C和D。
Which of the following is not true about dataflow graphs, take a look at AB and C and D.
哪一个？
Which one?
是C，对吧？所以是静态数据。
C, right? So static data.
数据流图意味着它是静态的。
Data flow graph means that it's static.
所以你只需要定义一次，它就会一直运行下去，适用于更大量的数据。
So you just define once and it will run forever for bitter data.
给定静态数据流图，批处理是很自然的，
And given static data graph, batching is natural, you
你只需要把批次扔进图里，它就会运行。
just throw batches into the graph and it will run.
因为形状是静态的。
Because the shape is static.
D选项很明显。
For D is obvious.
定义-运行是一种处理动态图数据的可行方式，
Define run is a possible way to handle dynamic data for graphs,
因为你并不关心性能问题。
because you don't care about performance.
那我们来看一下。好的。
So let's see. Okay.
很简单，对吧？这基本就是期末考试的难度水平。
Pretty easy, right? This is basically the level of difficulty in final exam.
好的，那我们回到今天的主要内容。
Okay. Yeah, let's go back to the main contents today.
我记得上节课我们讲了用基本操作来表达计算的表示方法，
So I think last lecture, we talk about representation that express the computation using primitives,
而这种表示其实就是数据流图。
and that repent is basically data flow graph.
我们还讲了如何在前向路径上定义数据流图，对吧？
And we also talk about how to define dataflow graph at the forward path, right?
但我们做的是深度学习，我们不会止步于此，因为我们还关心反向
But we are doing deep learning, we are not going to be ending there because we care about backward
图的反向传播，对吧？
graph back propagation, right?
我们想要优化模型的权重。
We want to optimize the model weights.
在本次讲座中，我们将从如何基本定义开始讲起。
So in this talk, we are going to talk about we're going to start with how to basically define
使用数据流图来定义反向竞争。
the backward competition using data flow graphs.
本次学习目标，首先我们会讲自动微分。
And this learning goal, we first talk about auto differentiation.
一旦你理解了这一点，
And once you understand that,
我就可以开始为你介绍机器学习系统中的核心问题。
I can start presenting you basically the grand problem of machine learning systems.
我们试图优化什么？
What do we try to optimize?
如果时间允许，我们还会讲一些更底层的内容，好吗？
And if time permits, we're going to talk about a little bit lower level things, okay?
那么，自动微分，对吧？
So, auto differentiation, right?
那我们在做自动微分的时候会做什么？
So what do we do when we do auto
我们基本上就是在求梯度和导数。
We basically take graditsT derivatives.
好吗？所以我希望你们还记得你们本科时学过的求导方法。
Okay? So I hope you still remember your undergrad course, how to take derivatives.
那么给定F Theta，什么是F对Theta的偏导数？
So given F Theta, what is partial F by Pi Theta?
我们可以按定义来求，就是这个极限，对吧？
So we can take it by definition, which is basically this limit, right?
所以我们找一个很小的epsilon，然后尝试求这个极限。
So we find a very small epson and we try to derive the limit.
这个在计算机程序中是可行的。
And this is doable in computer program.
我们要做的基本上就是分别计算F在Theta和Theta加epsilon处的值，
What do we do is basically we evaluate the function value F at Theta and Theta plus Epson,
然后我们就按照这个方法来做。
and then we just follow this right.
只要epsilon足够小，我们实际上就可以近似出梯度，
As long as apsnon is very small, we can actually approximate the grading,
对，也就是偏导数。
right, the partial derivative.
但这里的问题是什么？
But what is the problem here?
为什么DplingFramwork不用这个方法？
Why DplingFramwork does not use this one?
好，第一个问题是，它非常慢，对吧？
Okay, the first problem is, it's very slow, right?
因为每次我们都需要计算两个数值来得到一个梯度，一个导数，对吧？
Because every time we need to evaluate two values to get one gradient, one derivative, okay?
第二个问题是，这种方法不准确，因为它本质上是
Second problem is, this one is not accurate because it's it's basically we
我们在近似梯度值，对吧？
are approximating the grading values, right?
而且我们基本上是取足够小的间隔来做近似。
And we are basically take small enough apsion to approximate that.
你知道，计算机有很多浮点误差，如果你用这种方式，
You know, computer has a lot of floating point arrows, and if you do this way,
那些浮点误差会在整个神经网络中传播，我们
that floting point arrow will propagate all the way through neural network and we are
得不到准确的梯度。
not going to get accurate gradient.
所以实际上，我们不会这么做。
So in reality, we don't do this.
我们做的基本上是符号微分，基本上就是应用
What we do is basically we do symbolic differentiation, and we basically applied
我们从微积分课上学到的知识，尝试推导梯度或偏导数
what we learned from the calculus class and we try to derive the gradient or partial derivative
使用这些求导规则，对吧？
using these derivative rules, right?
希望你们还记得。如果不记得的话，回去看看，提醒一下自己。
I hope you still remember. If you don't take a look, okay, try to remind yourself, okay.
我们将要演示一个非常简单的例子。
And we are going to walk through a very simple example.
这里我们有一个非常小的计算过程，你也可以把它看作是神经网络，对吧？
So here we have a very small commutation, or you can also think this as neural network, right?
我们有两个输入X1和X2，然后进行一些计算
Were we have two inputs X one, X two, and going through some computation
我在这里定义了这个计算，非常简单。
which I defined here, pretty simple.
按照我们上节课讲的内容，
And following what we taught in the last lecture,
我们基本上把它画成计算图来可视化。
we basically write visualize it as commutation graph.
我们还为x1和x2赋值。
And we also instantiate the values for x1x2.
所以你可以看到，通过竞争机制我们实际上可以推导出结果Y的值。
So you can see, following the competon we can actually derive the value of the outcome, which is Y.
我们的目标是计算Y对X1的偏导数的值。
And our goal is we try to calculate the value of partial Y by partial X one.
例如，我们想对X1求导。
For example, we want to take the derivative against X one.
这就是我们在神经网络训练中通常做的事情。
That's what we normally do in neur twork training.
所以我们基本上遵循偏导数规则，还有链式法则，在这方面，
So we basically follow partial derivative rules, and also chain rules and um and in this regard,
我们实际上有两种方法。
we actually have two ways.
我在这里列出了，一种是前向方式，就是我们可以，
So which I list here, one is the forward way that is we can,
如果你看左边的函数，
if you look at the function on the left side,
你可以从左到右求导，对吧？
so you can take the derivative from left to right, right?
And you can calculate step by step from X, all the way to Y, that is from the inner of
the function to the outer part of the function.
Or you can do something that is taught in machine learning class that is back propagation.
You do from right to left, right?
You take the derivative Y against the
V six and the V five and then all the way back propagate through, um, X one and X two.
You can always get a results.
We are going to reason a little bit on these two modes, okay,
because there are a lot of softwares basically implementing two different kinds of modes.
Okay, we call the first mode, forward mode, auto differentiation or forward ED.
第二种模式，反向ED，明白吗？
The second mode, backward ED, okay?
那我们先来讲一下前向模式。
So let's first run through forward mode.
好的，前向模式的做法基本上是，我们要定义这个VI点。
Okay. The way we do forward mode is basically, we are going to define this VI dot.
这个点基本上被定义为VI对XI的偏导数。
The dot is basically defined as the partial derivative of VI against XI.
所以这就是图中的IS节点对应输入。
So that is the IS node in the graph against the input.
明白了吗？那我们要做的就是
Okay? So what do we do is we are going to our goal is try to
我们的目标是推导出偏导数∂Yi/∂X1的值，对吧？
derive the value of partial Yi partial X one, right?
那我们要做的就是从X1开始，一直到
So what do we do is we are going to start with from X one all the way
Y，我们要弄清楚怎么得到这个值。
to Y and we try to figure out how we can get that value.
所以其实很简单，对吧？
So it's pretty simple, right?
所以根据定义，呃，v一的导数基本上就是一，因为v一等于x一。
So by definition, uh, we one dot is basically one, right, because we one is equal to X one.
对，所以导数基本上就是一。
Right, so the dervative is basically one.
然后我们就一直这样做，按照图从左到右，
And we just do it all the way, following the graph from left to right,
最终我们会得到v七的导数，基本上是，呃，5.5。
and eventually we are going to reach we seven dot, which is basically, uh, 5.5.
好吗？我不会深入讲计算过程，但我觉得这个非常直接。
Okay? I'm not going to dive deep into the calculation, but I think this one is very straightforward.
你只需要一步一步来就行了。
You just do it step by step.
好，函数就是我的派系。好吧。
Okay, function my faction. Okay.
有什么问题吗？没问题的话，最后我们可以写出答案，
Any question? Cool. And finally, we can write the answer,
就是偏y对偏x一等于5.5，也就是v七的导数的值。
which is a partial Y by partial X one is equal to 5.5, which is equal to the value of V seven dot.
好，通过这个过程你可以看到，呃，呃，前向模式AD的特点。
Okay. And from this process, you can see, um, uh, the characteristics of forward forward mode 80,
基本上，我们从这里的输入节点开始，也就是X一或者X二。
basically, we start from the input node right here is X one or X two.
然后我们一直推导梯度，直到输出节点，这里是Y。
And we derive the gradient all the way to the opt nodes, here is Y.
那么，前向自动微分有什么优缺点呢？
So what is the pros and cons of forward auto diff?
或许让我问你一个问题。
Maybe let me ask you a question.
那Petrous用的是这种方法吗？
So does petrous use this one?
不是吧？对吧？那一定是有什么原因，
No, right? Yeah, there must be something that happening that,
让Petro没有采用这种方法。
you know, prevent Petro from using that.
那我们来稍微读一下。
So let's read it a little bit.
在更多的替代方法中，问题通常是我们在求解这个函数F，
So in for more alternative, the problem is we are usually solving this function F,
从N维空间的输入到K维空间的输出。
from N dimensional space input to a k dimensional space output.
为了求解关于输入X或X或XN的偏导数，
And in order to derive the partial Y against input X or X or X N,
我们基本上只需要进行一次前向传播，就能得到关于某个输入的梯度，对吧？
we basically need to run one forward pass to get the gradient with respect to one input, right?
所以如果我们有很多很多输入，那我们就需要……
So if we have many many inputs, then we need to.
比如说，在这里，如果N非常大，那我们就需要进行前向传播
So for example, here, if N is pretty large, then we need to run in forward pass
来获得从1到n每个X_i的梯度。在深度学习中，情况就是这样的。
to get the gradients against every X I from one to n. In deep learning, uh, this is the case.
基本上在深度学习中，在很多机器学习问题里，我们的输入维度很高，比如说，
Basically in deep learning, in many mansing problems, we have a high dimensional input, For example,
我们有很多参数，我们想要求出每个参数的梯度。
we have a lot of parameters, we want to derive the gradient against each parameter.
比如说GPT-3有1750亿个参数。
Like in GB three is 175 billion.
但我们只有一个输出，就是损失值。
But we only had one output that loss loss value.
比如说下一个token的预测损失或者分类损失。
For example, next token predicting loss or classification loss.
所以如果我们应用这个前向模式，
So if we apply this forward mode,
用80来做微分其实非常非常低效，因为我们需要对每一个参数输入都做
80 into deplening then it's very, very inefficient because we need to dp
梯度计算，并且我们需要运行的次数
gradients for each input that is a parameter, and we need to run as
就等于参数的数量。
many times as the number of parameters.
明白了吗？这就是为什么前向80其实对微分来说不是很有用。
Okay? That's why forward 80 is actually not very useful for deperning.
好的。但它其实很容易理解，因为你只需要从左到右
Okay. But it's very easy to think about, yeah, because you just go through
走一遍计算图就可以了。
the computing graph from left to right.
你不需要反向传播。
You don't need a backward pass.
好的。所以这基本上就引出了反向模式80，也就是反向模式自动微分，对吧？
Okay. So that basically brings us to the reverse mode 80 or backward mode 80, okay?
这里，我将花一些时间再跑一遍这个计算图，
Here, I'm going to, uh, spend some time to run through this graph again,
但是我们要应用反向模式ED，好吗？
but we are going to apply the reverse mode ED, okay?
所以为了运行这个实模式ED，呃，显然和外部模式不同，
So in order to run this real mode ED, uh, apparently different from the foreign mode,
我们要从Y一路回溯到XR乘以二。
we are going to run from Y all the way back to XR x two.
好吗？为了实现这个，我们要引入一个新的定义，叫做joint。
Okay? And in order to run that, we are going to bring a new definition that is joint.
好的，这里我定义V bar等于Y的偏导数。
Okay? Here I define the V bar equals to partial Y.
关于I的偏导数，也就是输出
By partial I, that is the partial derivative of the output
Y对当前节点I的偏导数。是的，
Y against the current node I. Yeah,
I基本上就是索引节点。
I is basically the index node.
我们基本上要反向计算每个I bar，对不起，是反向，不是反向
We are going to basically compute each I bar in the reverse, sorry, reverse not reverse
是图的反向拓扑顺序，从Y一路回溯。
reverse topological order of the graph, from Y all the way back.
So here's the commutation.
We are going to run a few equations, and then, um, probably you can take
more time to understand the rest.
So for the first one, uh, seven bar is basically like we are teaching partial derivative of we are
taking partial derivative of partial Y against partial seven, right?
Because Y basically equals to with seven, so the value is one, right, identity function.
And then we run to the second equation, which is, partial, sorry, with six bar.
And I hope you still remember chain rule, right?
So when we take the partial partial Y against with six,
we basically change the gradient of partial Y against seven and the partial derivative
V七对六，对吧？
of V seven against six, right?
我们把它们绑在一起，是的。
We tie them together, yeah.
然后我们基本上得到六杠。
And we basically get six bar.
我们用链式法则一个一个地做，这个你在神经网络课上学过，
And we do this one by one using the chain room, which you learned in the neuralnetwork class,
然后我们基本上可以一路反向传播到X一，
and we can basically run all the way back to X one,
我们基本上可以得到一杠和二杠的值，
and we basically can get the value of 1 bar and two bar,
就在这里，你可以看到它的值也是5.5，这和公式是一样的。
which is there, and you can see the value is also 5.5, which is equal to the form.
好的，这里还有一点我需要补充说明，
Okay. Um, here, there's a little bit one more thing I need to mention that is,
你可以看到对于第三周和第二周，当我们计算
you can see for week three and we two, when we take the when we calculate the value of
W三杠和二杠的值时，这里会稍微复杂一些。
W three by and we 2 bars a little bit more difficult complicated here.
也就是说，我们有这样一种类似图结构的东西，对吧？
That is, we have this kind of like a graph structure, right?
在这里，w1 基本上同时影响 w2 和 w。
Here, we one basically contributes to both we two and with.
而 w4 有两个输入。
And we four has two inputs.
分别是 w 和 w。那么你还记得怎么推导
That is wet and W. So do you still remember how to derive
这种结构的梯度吗？
the gradients of this kind of like structure?
所以它需要两条路径才能到达 Y 的结果。
So it takes we want two paths to reach the outcome of Y.
那么我们怎么求梯度呢？
So how do take the grading.
其实很简单，对吧？基本上 t 已经完成了，对吧？
It's pretty simple, right? So basically t is done, right?
所以我们想要的就是 ∂Y/∂V1，基本上我们就是展开这个函数
So we want byte basically equal to partial Y by partial V one, and we basically enroll the function
Y。把 Y 作为 w2 和 w 的函数来展开。
Y. Enroll Y as a function of we two and we.
我们还发现我们对W一进行函数运算。
And we also find we we are function over W one.
所以我们只需要使用偏导数规则，一直写下去就行了。
So we just use partial derivative rules and write it all the way.
这样我们基本上得到了这个方程，就是抛物线乘以偏导数。
So we basically get the equation that is throw bar times the partial derivative we
两个对比项和第二项。
two against and the second term.
明白了吗？这就是这里发生的事情。
Okay? That's what happened here.
这两条方程里发生了什么。
What happened here in these two equations.
好的。好的。这只是个热身，好吗？
Okay. Okay. This is just a warm up, okay?
希望你们还记得这些内容。
I hope you'll still remember all this.
这基本上就是基础微积分，对吧？
Okay? This is basically basic calculus, right?
如果我们稍微推广一下，其实我们可以推导出
So if we generalize a little bit, we can basically derive
这个说法是针对数据流图中的节点，对吧？对于被多个消费者使用的节点，
this statement that is for node in the data flow graph, right for we one used by multiple consumers,
我们基本上可以这样计算，这个联合Wi bar等于
we can basically calculate this at joint Wi bar equals to
也就是说，基本上是它所有消费者的总和，对吧？
so basically the sum of all the all its consumers, right?
在这里，我们又定义了另一个术语，就是Wii到J bar，好吗？
And here, we define another term which is Wii two J bar, okay?
其中I到G bar基本上是WJ bar乘以Wig对其中一个的偏导数。明白了吗？
Where I two G bar is basically WJ bar times the partial derivative Wig against one. Okay?
这基本上就是分叉。
This is like, basically bifurcation.
有什么问题吗？没问题吧。我们都明白了，对吧？这很简单的数学。
Any question? Cool. We are good, right? Pretty simple math.
好的。那么现在，基本上你已经理解了前向模式AD和反向模式AD。
Okay. Then now, you basically, understand both forward mode 80 and backward mode 80.
我们现在要总结一下反向模式AD，好吗？
And we are going to summarize a little bit about backward mode 80, okay?
在反向模式AD中，补偿的工作流程基本上是从输出节点开始的，对吧？
So in backward mode 80, compensation workflow is basically start from output nodes, right?
And we derive the grading all the way back to the input nodes,
which is a reverse order or for mode 80.
So what is the pros and cons of backward mode 80, sorry, this is backward mode.
So basically the pros of, uh, forward mode, it is the cons of the backward mode 80, right?
Because here, still, we have a function of wishing maps from N dimensional space
to a key dimensional space.
And if we want to take gradients, uh, using the backward mode,
we basically need the backward pass to get gradient with respect to all the inputs.
Okay. But like I said, why this one is adopted in deploying?
Because in deploying K is pretty small.
N 是不是很高？很大，对吧。好的。
N is pretty high, right? Pretty large. Okay.
这就是为什么反向模式，自动微分基本上是默认的微分规则，
That's why backward mode, AD is, um, uh, basically the default, uh, a differentiate rules that
我们在部署库和合并系统时都会用到。
we use in deploying libraries in merging systems.
但是要记住，在其他领域，如果我们的 K 很大，
Okay. But remember that in other areas where we have a pretty large K,
但 a 很小，我们还是可以回去用正向模式。
but a small, we can still go back to use four mode.
比如说，在很多科学计算场景下，
For example, in many many scientific computing scenarios, yeah, where we don't we have
输入维度很低，但输出维度很高。
low dimensional input, but high dimis output.
对。好的，那我们回到我们的问题。
Yeah. Okay. Then back to our question.
现在，你已经理解了自动微分的底层机制。
Now, you understand the underlying mechanisms of ED.
但要记住，我们的目标是用自动微分推导数据流图，因为我们
But remember, our mission is we try to use ED to derive dataflow graphs because we
想要一些可以代表竞争的东西，对吧？
want something that can represent the competition, right?
ED 帮助我们获得梯度，但我们想把 ED 写进计算图里。
ED helps us to get the gradients, but we want to write ED into the graph.
好的。那么我们如何构建一个可以计算梯度的竞争图呢？
Okay. So how can we construct a competition graph that calculates the gradients?
我们知道梯度可以通过伴随值来计算。
We know that gradients can be calculated from the adjoint values.
所以本质上，我们要定义一个可以计算伴随值的计算图，对吧？
So essentially how we can, uh define computer graph that calculate the adjoin values, right?
好吗？我来告诉你答案。
Okay? I'm going to give you the answer.
我会带大家过一遍这个算法。
I'm going to run through this algorithm.
基本上，所有不同的库其实都用这个算法。
Basically, all the different libraries they basically use this algorithm.
这个算法基本上就是用反向模式 AD 来计算梯度的。
This is algorithm that basically calculate the gradients using backward mode 80.
我会稍微带大家过一遍这个算法，好吗？
I'm going to run through this algorithm a little bit okay?
我休息的方式是，我要给你举一个换元的例子，嗯，这个换元
The way I rest, I'm going to give you an example commutation, um and the commutation
基本上就是一个非常简单的函数F，它会接收一个输入，取指数再加一，
is basically very simple function F, which will take one input, take exponential plus one as in
然后再乘以u本身，得到输出。
times u itself and get the output.
但在我们运行这个数据流图上的算法之前，我们要做什么呢？我想给你
But before we run the uh algorithm on this dataflow graph, what do we do I try to give you
一个关于这个算法整体流程的高层次描述。
a high level picture of what's going on in that algorithm.
好的，我们来逐行阅读它。
Okay. Let's read it line by line.
基本上，我们是想要获取某个特定节点的梯度，对吧？
So basically, we want to take the gradients of a specific node, right?
所以我们会维护一个节点的所有偏导aljoint。
So we are going to maintain all partial joints of a node.
因为一旦我们有了偏导aljoint的列表，就可以把它们加在一起，
Because once we have a list of partial aljoints can sum them together,
我们就能得到梯度值，对吧？
we get the gradient value, right?
这就是我在上一页幻灯片中定义的内容。
That's what I defined in my previous slide.
所以这个结构基本上会尝试为每个节点的所有偏伴随值进行优化。
So this organ will basically try to opt the values for all the partial adjoints for each node.
获取这些值的方法，首先是遍历图结构，
The way you get the values basically first, it traverse the graph
按照反向拓扑顺序遍历，这是由反向模式定义的，
following a reverse topological order that is defined by backward mode
没错，因为我们必须以这种方式遍历。
80 right because we have to traverse in that way.
我们的做法是，首先把该节点的所有偏导数加起来，
And what we do is, uh, we first, sum all the partial algoin of that node
这样才能得到它的偏导数总和。
together in order to get its partial duptive.
这样说有道理吗？这就是定义本身，好吗？
Does that make sense? That is by definition, okay?
然后，一旦我们得到了这个节点的偏导数，
And then once we have the partial derivative of this node,
接下来我们要做的就是查看它的输入节点。
what do we do is we are going to look at is input node.
也就是说，所有对这个节点有贡献的节点。
That is, that is, all the nodes that contribute to this one node.
明白了吗？在ph图上有指向这个节点的入边。
Okay? Have incoming edge on the ph graph to this node.
我们要计算部分伴随，明白吗？
And we are going to compute the partial adjoint, okay?
这里，对于任意输入K，我们计算B，K到I bar，根据定义就是这个方程，对吧？
Here is for any input K, we compute B, K to I bar, which is by definition this equation, right?
好的，然后我们会把这个值更新到那个节点，就是索引为K的节点，对吧？
Okay. And then we are going to update this value into that node, which is with index of K, right?
也就是说，下次我们按照奖励顺序遍历图时，
That is next time we traverse the graph following the rewards order,
我们会访问这个K节点，就在这里。
we are going to visit this K, right here.
我们基本上会得到部分的导数。
We are going to get it basically partial duptive.
明白了吗？你可以看到这个程序基本上是递归的，对吧，因为它会
Okay? And you can see this program is basically recursive, right, because it will go
一直回溯到IR节点。
through all the way back to the IR node.
它会遍历这个节点，基本上会返回它的值。
It traverse or the node, and basically it will return the value of this.
这正是我们想要的，对吧。好的。
That's what we want. Right. Okay.
关于这个程序有什么问题吗？好的。
Any question about this program. Okay.
我们来过一遍这个。我想我已经解释过了。
Let's run through this. I think I already explained this.
这个基本上就是把所有的部分连接加起来，得到梯度或者部分。
This one is basically sum up all the partial joints to get the gradient or partial
dtiveT 这个是计算并将部分连接传播到它的输入。
dtiveT one is compute and propagates the partiality joints to its inputs.
我们来过一遍这个，好吗。
Let's run through this, okay.
所以给定这个图，我们将按照奖励的拓扑顺序来操作，
So given this graph, we are going to follow the rewards topological order,
我们将从
we are going to start from
W四开始，也就是最后一个节点。
W four, which is the last node.
这里，i 等于四，我在这里做个记录。
And here, I equals to four, which I take note here.
然后我们基本上要运行这行代码，对吧？
And we are going to basically, uh, run this line, right?
我们发现对于开放节点，呃，w4 它只有一个部分偏导，就是一等于一。
And we find that for the open node, uh, we four it only has one partial aloin which is one equal
因为这是恒等函数，没有什么特别的。
to one because it's identity function, nothing special.
所以我们基本上把它们加在一起，呃，发现这个值基本上就是一。
So we basically something together, uh, and we find that the value is basically one.
现在我想在我的图中表示这个结果。
And now I want to represent this in my graph.
所以我选择了一个更方便的方法，就是直接赋值一，
So I basically choose a more convenient method that is directly assign value one,
直接赋值给一个叫做 wifour bar 的节点。
right to a node called wifour bar.
这个函数其实就是恒等函数。
And this function is basically identity.
好的，这一行我们就完成了，对吧？
Okay. And we finish this line, right?
接下来的步骤基本上就是进入那个内循环。
And the next step is basically we go into that inner loop.
好的，我们要检查所有对WFO有贡献的节点。
Okay, we are going to check all the nodes that basically contribute values into
然后我们尝试推导这个部分伴随量。
WFO and we try to derive this partial adjoint.
好的，这里我们要检查两件事，对吧？
Okay. Uh, here we are going to inspect two things, right?
一个是W二到wafer的配对，因为
One is the pair W two to wafer because
WIR是二的函数，第二个是wi到wi四。
WIR is a function of two and the second is wi wi four.
好的，同时我们基本上要把这个过程记录下来。
Okay. Um, meanwhile, we are going to basically, uh, document this.
我们要记录这个最后一个节点的梯度，对吧。
We are going to record this last note grad, right.
在这里你可以看到，当K等于的时候，
And here, um, you can see, when K equals to,
所以这里i等于四，并且我们已经有了W四的伴随量。
so here I equals to four and we already have W four bar,
我们将从输入I的列表开始，我们知道输入I
and we are going to start from the list inputs I and we know that input I
基本上等于wet或者with three，对吧？
basically equals to either wet or with three, right?
所以我们将从K等于2开始，对吧？
So we are going to start from K equals to two, right?
然后我们要运行这个程序，好吗？
And we are going to run this program, okay?
所以我们有224 bar等于
So we 224 bar equals
W四bar乘以偏导we four对W二的偏导，对吧？
W four bar times partial we four by partial W two, right?
而且我们已经有了w四bar的值，就是在这里。
And we already have the value of w four bar, which is here.
我们给它赋值为1。
We assigned a value equal to one.
然后我们要写下这个值224 bar，以及如何用数据流图表示它。
And we are going to write down this value with 24 bar, and how to represent as dataflow graph.
我们发现偏导four对W二的偏导基本上等于with three，对吧？
We find that the partial four by partial W two is basically equal to equal to with three, right?
因为在这里，你可以看到，我们的四等于wei两次乘以三。
Because here, you can see, we four equals to wei two times with three.
所以如果你取偏导数，基本上我们的值是和三有关，对吧？
So if you take the partial derivative, basically our value is with three, right?
所以为了表示这个wei二到四的bar，我们以这样的方式构建一个图
So in order to represent this way two to four bar, we construct a graph in a way
就是我们把它和三节点连接起来，
that we connect this with three node and
W四bar，操作符基本上是乘法，对吧？
W four bar and the operator basically is multiplier, right?
所以我们基本上得到了wei 224 bar的重复。
So we basically get the repetition of wei 224 bar.
好，有什么问题吗？记住，我们的目标是把所有内容都用图来表示。
Okay. Any question? So remember, our goal is we try to represent everything in graph.
是的，因为一旦我们有了这个图，我们就可以表示前向和反向两种情况。
Yeah, because once we have that graph, we can represent both forward and backward.
好的，同样的事情，对吧，我们可以运行。
Okay. And same thing, right, we can run.
我们完成了K等于二，然后我们向前移动到下一个三节点，
We finish the K equal to two, then we move forward to the next node with three,
对，这也是对Wi四的另一个贡献者。
right, which is another contributor to Wi four.
同样的道理，我们基本上应用那个规则。
And same thing, we basically apply that rule.
所以，三到四的bar等于wei四乘以四对三的偏导。
So with three to four bar equals to wei four times partial four by partial with three.
四对三的偏导基本上等于W二，对吧，因为它是相乘的。
And partial wi four partial three is basically equal to W two, right, because it's multiply.
我们对乘数求导，所以结果是w四部分乘以W二。
We take a directive against multiplier, and so the value is w four part times W two.
这就是为什么我们在这里加了一个乘数，对吧？
That's why we basically add an multiplier here, right?
所以我们用w四部分和W二相乘，得到with bar。
So we multiply with four part and W two, and we get with bar.
呃，其实我们没有得到with bar。
Uh, actually, we didn't get with bar.
我们得到的是三到四的bar，但我们发现with三只有一个输入。
We get with three to four part, but we found that with three only has, uh, one input.
另一个输入是常数。
The other input is constant.
所以基本上这两个值是一样的，对吗？
So basically these two values are the same, right?
对。所以为了简单起见，我们基本上，呃，呃，创建了另一个带有 bar 的节点，
Right. So for the simplicity, we basically, uh, uh, create another node which is with bar,
然后我们把它放在这里。
and we put it here.
明白了吗？还跟得上吧？
Okay? Still follow, right?
很好。这意味着这个循环完成了第一次迭代，我们在 I 等于 with four 时结束，
Cool. That means that this loop finish the first iteration, we finish with I equals to with four,
然后我们继续，好吗？
and then we proceed. Okay?
同时，记住，我们要在这里记录每个节点的所有部分伴随值。
And meanwhile, remember, we are going to document all the partial adjoint here for each node.
好的。然后我们继续运行这个，接着回到 with
Okay. And then we continue run this and we go back to with
three，因为我们用的是逆拓扑顺序。
three because we are using a reverse topological order.
所以我们回到 with three。
So we go back to with three.
我们基本上做的就是发现对于w3来说已经完成了，对吧，因为我们
And what we do is basically we find that with three is already done right because we
w3只有一个部分伴随，所以我们只需要把它们加在一起，就是这里。
three only has one partial adjoint, so we just sum them together, which is here.
好的。然后我们进入这个内循环，检查有多少个节点，
Okay. And then we go into this inner loop and we inspect how many nodes,
呃，对w3有贡献，我们发现只有k2到w2，对吧？
uh, contribute to with three, and we find that there's only cakes to two, we two, right?
所以我们基本上就是尝试计算w2到w3的伴随，
Uh, so we basically take we basically try to calculate the wei two to three bar,
按照公式，我们得到w3的伴随乘以偏导数，
uh, and following the equation, we get with three bar times partial by partial way,
然后我们得到的这个值其实就是w2的伴随本身，对吧？
two, and we get this value is basically with bar itself, right?
就是这样。
So, yeah.
然后我们继续按照反向拓扑顺序，回到了W2。
And we continue following the reverse topic order, and we get back to W two.
在这个例子中，我们发现w2实际上是输入w1的一个复杂函数。
Okay? In this example, we found we two is actually a expensive function of the input that we one.
好吗？所以在这里，我们首先按照这个方程，我们发现我们有两个部分联合。
Okay? So here, we first follow this equation, we found that we two has two partial joint.
所以我们把它们加在一起，对吧。
So we sum them together, right.
然后在这里我们把它们加在一起。
And here we sum them together.
这两个部分联合基本上就是我们两个，两个四杆和我们223杆，对吧？
And these two partial joints basically we two, two, four bar and we 223 bar, right?
根据数据流图，我们基本上添加了两条边并把它们加在一起，
Following the data photograph, we basically add two edges and sum them together,
然后我们得到了我们两个杆，好吗？
and we results into we two bar, okay?
然后我们进入内循环，当k等于1时，我们尝试计算我们想要的杆。
And then we run into the inner loop, and when cake to one, we try to calculate we want to burn.
按照方程，我们得到了这个，基本上就是这个结果。
Following equation, we get this uh basically this result.
为了把这个表示到数据流图中，我们要做的是连接这个节点。
In order to represent this into Dataflograph, what we do is we are going to connect this node.
还有指数一的值。
And the value of exponential one.
我们发现一的指数值本质上是方式二。
And we find that the exponential value of one is essentially way two.
所以我们在这里再加一条边，这样我们就得到了122杠。
So we add another edge all the way here, and that gives us uh we 122 bar.
我们还发现一没有任何输入。
And we also find out one does not have any input.
所以我们12杠基本上等于1杠。
So we 12 bar basically equals to 1 bar.
我们就稍微简化一下这个图，并在这里创建另一个指向1杠的节点。
So we basically simplify the graph a little bit and create another node to 1 bar here.
好的，这基本上就是我们如何通过数据流图运行这个算法的过程。
Okay. That's basically how we run this algorithm through data pho graph.
当我们向前运行数据流图时，我们还会创建
And as we run through, forward data photograph, we also create
另一个与数据流图相连的图。
another graph that connected to the photograph.
那就是我们的反向图，也就是这个图中红色的部分。
That is our backward graph, which is the red part of this graph.
好，有什么问题吗？好的，很棒。
Okay. Any question? Okay, cool.
如果你在理解过程中有任何困难，呃，可以回去再看一下这张幻灯片。
If you have any trouble following any part of this, uh, go back and take a look at this slide.
我觉得这很清楚。只要稍微想一想，我们就能弄明白。
I think it's pretty clear. Just think a little bit and it we figure out.
好的，总结一下，呃，在这个过程中，我们基本上做的事情是
Okay. So in summary, uh, during this process, what we do is basically we
以符号化的方式构建反向图。
construct the backward graph in a symbolic way.
嗯，我们实际上并没有计算具体的数值，对吧？
Um, we don't actually calculate the values, right?
这样做的原因是我们真的非常需要这个图，因为就像在神经网络中一样，
And the reason is because we really, really want this graph because like in neural network,
我们会输入不同类型的数据，而数据会在这个图中流动。
we are going to give different kind of data and the data will run risk graph.
我们不能只进行一次计算，因为这个计算应该
And we cannot just do one time competition because this competon should be
适用于所有不同类型的数据批次。
applied to all different kind of databtches.
所以有了这个图，不管输入是什么，我们都可以推导出接下来的内容。
So given this graph, we can basically, uh, whatever input it comes, we are going to derive following
竞争定义图可以被重复使用。
the competon defining graph, it can be reused.
这个在tf patric中很常用。
And this one is commonly used in tf patric.
好的，现在让我们来推理一下，分析一下权衡。
Okay. Now let's do reasoning reason a little bit, okay on the trade offs.
在典型的机器学习课程中，
So So in a typical machine learning class,
我认为老师会教你，比如说反向传播。
I think the teacher will tell you, we'll teach you like bipagon.
记住反向传播，基本上就是你拿左边的图，
And remember B propagation, basically, you take that left figure and
然后你做一次反向传递。
you run a backward pass through.
但在这门课里，我们实际上并不做反向传播。
But in this class, we are actually not doing backprogion.
我们做的是反向模式，完全不同。
We are doing reverse mode allots different.
为什么？因为在这里，我们要构建一个反向图，并且把反向图连接到
Why? Because in set, we are going to construct a backward graph and we connect the backward graph to
照片，然后我们得到一个更大的图。
the photograph and we get even bigger graph.
在大约十年前最初的机器学习框架设计中，
And in the initial set of machine learning frameworks design like ten years ago,
他们实际上就是用的那种模式。
they are actually using that mode.
所以基本上在系统中，他们用的是反向传播。
So basically in the system, they are using back propagation.
他们从不构建反向图。
So they never construct a backward graph.
他们只是拿着前向图，获取梯度并传播梯度。
They just take the photograph and take the gradients and propagated gradients.
但在现代深度学习框架中，我们采用了这种图的方法，也就是，
But in the modern dpling frameworks, we are using this graph approach, that is,
我们会构建反向图，而且几乎每个框架都在用这种方式进行计算。
we construct the backward graph, and it has been used by basically every framework to prog.
所以我的问题是，为什么这种方式变得更流行了？
So my question is why this one become more popular.
就是说，为什么我们要关心得到一个反向图呢？
Like, why do we care about getting a Brograph? Yeah.
信息，没错。
Information Exactly.
这是一个主要原因，因为如果你只有照片，那么你的系统只会读取
That's one primary reason, because if you only have photograph, then your system will only read
照片，你只能在表示方式上进行优化。
the phograph and you can optimize over representation.
但如果你还有一个背景图，你的系统可以——我的系统并不关心回溯。
But if you also have a background graph, your system can my system does not care about for backward.
我只有一个视角，就是给定一个计算图。
I only have one perspective that I'm given a computing graph.
我要去优化其他的图，对吧？
I'm going to optimize other graph, right?
所以我们基本上想要一个对整个计算过程的整体表示。
So we basically want a holistic representation of the competition.
还有其他原因吗？
Any other reason?
没错。
Exactly.
这非常适用。
It's very amenable.
比如说，你可能知道现在的边际模型可以非常复杂。
So for example, you probably know that today's marginy model can be very complicated.
有时候你需要对梯度再求梯度。
Sometimes you need to take the gradient of the gradient.
如果你用那种模式，如何对梯度或梯度的梯度求导就会非常困难，因为梯度
If you do that mode, how to take the gradient or gradients very difficult because the gradient
被隐藏在图的某个地方。
is hidden somewhere in the graph.
但在图的右侧，你可以看到梯度被明确地
But in the right side of the graph, you see the gradient is explicitly
表现在图中，那你该怎么做呢？
represented in the graph and what do you do?
如果你的计算需要计算梯度或梯度的梯度，
If your competition needs to care calculate the gradient or gradient,
你只需要在上面加更多的节点，自动库基本上会帮你
you just add more nodes on top of that, the Autolibrary will basically help
按照计算过程推导出梯度。
you derive the gradients following the competition.
好的，换句话说，这个图基本上就代表了整体的……
Okay. So in other words, this graph it represents the holistic basically, uh,
就像是对竞争的表示，这对系统来说非常友好，因为系统并不
like representation of the competition, and it's very friendly to systems because system does not
在意语义机会层。
care about semantics opportunity layer.
我只关心竞争。
I only care about competition.
明白了吗？呃，我要详细讲的第三个原因是
Okay? Uh a third reason which I'm going to talk about in
因为我们这里还缺少一些东西。
detail is because we are still missing some piece here.
那么如果我们想完成深度学习程序，还缺什么呢？
So what is missing if we want to complete the deep learning program?
我们有前向传播，也有反向传播。
We hold forward, we held backward.
是的，我们还需要梯度更新。
Yeah, we need a grading update.
如果你采用这种方法，那么你的梯度更新规则就会被隔离。
If you do this approach, then your grading update rule is going to be isolated.
你将会自己编写优化器。
You are going to write your own optim.
但是如果你使用这种模式，你可以继续添加
But if you do this mode, what you do is you can continue adding
一个或多个代表梯度更新的节点。
one and more nodes that represent the grading update.
在后面的课程中，特别是在arm部分，我们会发现梯度更新是
In the later lectures, especially in the arm sessions, we'll find that grading updates is one of
最消耗内存的操作之一，我们将对其进行优化。
the most memory consuming operations, and we are going to optimize it.
如果我们有该部分的图表示，那么系统查看起来会非常容易。
And if we have a graph repton for that part, then it's pretty easy for the system to look at that.
好的，现在让我们试着完成这一部分，好吗？
Okay. Now, let's try to finish this part, okay.
我们将把这个应用到实际操作中。
We are going to put this into practice.
抱歉，我们要回到我们的主方程，并且我们将
Sorry. We are going to go back to our mass equations and we are going to instiate
用几个模型来实例化这个主方程。
this master equation using a few models.
那就是一个简单的回归模型和一个两层神经网络。
That is a simple regression model, two layer neural network.
我们有两个权重，W一和W二，还有一个输入X。
We have two ways W one, W two, one input X.
这个输入会经过一个非线性函数，然后这个值会被用来和
Uh, this will go through a nonlinear function, and then the value will be compared to
真实值Y进行均方误差损失的比较。
the ground Y using mean square loss.
为了表示这个两层神经网络，我们基本上要做的是，顺便说一句，
And in order to represent this two layer neural network, what we do is basically, by the way,
我们这里还有一个梯度更新规则。
we also have a grading update rules here.
也就是说，每次我们拟合批数据时，我们都会得到梯度，然后我们会按照
That is every time we fit the bat, we are going to get gradients and we are going to follow
这个规则来更新参数。
this rule to update the updated parameters.
为了把它表示成一个神经网络，我们实际上有三个部分，
And in order to represent this as a neural network, we essentially have three parts,
你需要记住这一点。
and you need to remember this.
每次我们尝试表示新的神经网络结构时，
Every time we try to represent the new net recommendation,
你不需要照片。我们有三个部分。
you don't need photograph. We have three parts.
第一部分是前向，对吧？我们定义照片。
The first part is forward, right? We define photograph.
然后我们使用自动微分库
And then we take the auto differentiation library
基本上自动推导出反向传播过程，
to basically automatically derive the backward pass,
这个我已经在前面的幻灯片里讲过了。
which I already ran through, in the previous slides.
那部分你不需要做，因为Pat会帮你完成。
And that part, you don't have to do that because Pat will do that for you.
第三部分，正如我刚才提到的，你需要进行更新操作。
And the third part as I mentioned, you need to perform with the update.
现在我要，我们要把这些内容整合到一张图里。
Now I'm going to we're going to put all this together into one graph.
对于前向，呃，定义是一样的，节点代表操作符和它的势能，
So for forward, uh, uh, same definition, nodes represent the operator and it's a potential,
边则代表数据流动的方向。
and the edges represent the data flowing directions.
前向过程其实很简单。
For forward is pretty straightforward.
我们有X和W。
We have X and W one.
它们经过Melmo，一直到MSE损失。
They go to Melmo and all the way to the MSE loss.
然后你把它交给Petrog，我们将在Petrog中推导
And then you give it to Petrog and the petrog we are going to derve the
反向过程，按照我刚刚讲的流程。
backward following what I just uh went through.
好的。关键部分是我们还需要添加优化器操作。
Okay. And the critical part is we also need to add the optim meter operator.
那么如何添加优化器操作呢？
So how to add op meters.
这其实就是找到优化器的更新规则，然后连接一些节点，
That is what we basically find out the op meter update rules and we connect some nodes,
对吧？我们更新参数。
right? We update parameters.
好吗？非常简单。
Okay? Uh, very simple.
基本上，在右侧你可以看到一个完整的图，代表了这个新网络。
Basically, in the right hand side, you basically see a full graph that represent this new network.
而且这个图可以变得任意复杂，对吧？
And this can go arbitrary complex, right?
记住，实际上这就是一个有成千上万个节点的神经网络，
Remember, in reality, this is a neural network with thousands of nodes
包括前向传播、反向传播和参数更新。
with forward, backward and updates.
所以这个图可以由底层的系统来维护。
So this graph could be maintained by a system at a lower level.
好，作为作业，我们要实现这个自动微分库，
Yeah. Okay, as a homework, we are going to implement this auto different library
用我给你们的一些算子来实现。
with a few operators I give it to you.
其中一个算子就是softmax，这是一个非常有趣的算子。
And one operator is basically softmax, and this is a very interesting operator.
我认为它的表达形式非常优雅，你们要来实现它。
I think it's greeting is a very uh elegant form, and you are going to do this.
好的，酷。这基本上就是自动微分的全部内容，有什么问题吗？
Okay. Cool. That basically covers auto differentiation. Any question?
好的，一旦你理解了所有的微分概念，
Okay, once you understand all the differentiation,
我认为现在是介绍机器学习系统架构概览的合适时机。
I think it's the right time to introduce the architecture overview of machine learning systems.
那么人们在这里都在做些什么呢。
So what people are cooking here.
就像我刚才说的，不是吗，
So as I said, no,
如果我给你一个神经网络，你会像这样用数据流图来表示吗？
I give you a neural network, you are going to represent as a data flow graph like that?
这是一个来自TensorFlow的非常棒的动画。
Pretty nice animation from tensor flow.
它有输入节点，数据会在这个图中流动。
It has input nodes, I have data flowing through that graph.
对于这个图，它同时表示了前向传播、反向传播和参数更新。
For that graph, it also represents both forward, backward, and we update.
那么我们的系统目标是什么呢？
So what is our system go here?
我们的系统其实很简单，对吧。
So our system is pretty simple, right.
我们尽量让这个过程非常快，因为我们想要优化
We try to make this very fast, because we want to optiment
系统以实现最佳性能。
the system to achieve the best performance.
所以我们的系统目标基本上就是让它运行得非常快。
So our system go here is basically we try to make it fast so it can run super fast.
其次，我们还要让它具备可扩展性，对吧？
Secondly, we try to make it scale, right?
因为有时候你不能只用一张GPU来运行，所以你需要扩展到
Because sometimes you cannot run the scrap on a single GPU, so you need to scale this
很多很多GPU上，这样才能更快。
to many many GPUs to make it even faster.
我们还要确保它的内存使用高效，因为你已经知道GPU内存
We want to make sure it's memory efficient because you already know that GPU memory is
是非常稀缺的资源，为了处理像GPD三这样的模型，
very scare resources in order to treat models like GPD three,
你必须优化你的系统，让内存使用尽可能高效。
you have to basically optimize your system to use the memory as efficient as possible.
有时候我们还希望能在不同的硬件上运行，
And sometimes we want to run on diverse hardware,
GPU、CPU、iPhone 或其他设备。
GPU CPU, iPhone or whatever.
对，我们努力确保这个图可以在不同的平台上运行，好吗？
Yeah. Okay. We try to make sure this graph can run across different platforms, okay?
而且我们不希望消耗太多能源，因为我们需要为电费买单，
And we don't want to consume a lot of energy, because we have to pay for the electricity,
当然，这一点你们已经知道了。
of course, you already know this.
我们努力确保用户能够非常容易地
We try to make sure that users feel very easy to
编程或调试这个神经网络数据流图，好吗？
program or debug this neur network dataflow graph. Okay?
这基本上就是机器学习系统人员试图解决的问题范围。
That is basically a spectrum of problems that merchant learning system people are trying to solve.
好吗？也就是说，给定一个图，给定一些硬件，你要努力实现这些目标。
Okay? That is given a graph, given some hardware, you try to achieve these goals.
我接下来会给大家一个概述，这是一个非常非常简化的概述，
I'm going to give you an overview and it's a very, very simplified overview of how people realize
讲述人们如何在现有的机器学习框架中实现这些，比如Petro和Interflow。
this in the existing machine learning frameworks like Petro and interflow.
Um, maybe frameworks can be different, but basically, my overview
will apply to all these frameworks.
So in the future, uh, maybe when you start working on something,
you can try to map some code written in your framework into these layers and think
about what their functionality are, right?
So at the higher layer, maybe start from there.
We have a data ph graph, right, and we have a cluster of GPUs.
Okay? And at the higher layer, we already know that we are going to
represent the neuralnetwork as the data flow graph.
And there are some auto differentiation libraries that will basically take your photograph,
将反向传播连接在一起，以便用更新来表示。
drupe the backward and connect them together to represent with updates.
这两部分我们已经讲过了。
These two parts we already covered.
好的，这只是加工系统的高层部分。
Okay. And this is only the higher layer of machining systems.
为了加快速度，系统人员实际上在这背后构建了很多层。
In order to make it fast, uh, the system people actually build a lot layers behind this.
他们会做一个所谓的图增强层。
So what they do is they will do a so called graph augmentation layer.
那什么是图增强呢？
So what is graph opening?
我很快会给你一个概述。
I will give you a overview pretty soon.
但你可以理解为用户编写的那个图可能效率不高。
But you can understand that that graph, which is written by the user may be inefficient.
然后系统会拿到那个图，尝试进行一些分析，
Then the system will take that graph and try to analyze it a little bit to make
使其变成一个更高效的版本。
it more efficient version.
这可以通过许多现有的图论方法或各种图变换来实现。
And this can be done using many existing graph theory or whatever kind of graph transformation.
是的，基本上我试图推导出一个与初始图等价的图，
Yeah. Basically, I try to derive a graph that is equivalent with the initial graph,
但是第二个，也就是新的图会高效得多。
but the second one will be the new one will be much more efficient.
这就是我们称之为图增强的一个层次。
That is a layer we call graph augmentation.
明白了吗？在petrogentener流中，有很多代码其实就是在做图增强。
Okay? And in petrogentener flow, there are so many codes that is basically doing graph augmentation.
图增强之后，我们可以选择性地加入一个并行分区层。
And after Graph organization, what we try to do is we can optionally have a parledtion layer.
也就是说，我们试图把这个图分布到多个GPU上。
That is we try to distribute this graph on many GPOs.
但我说这个层是可选的，因为如果你的图在
But I said this layer is optional because if your graph is fine on
单个GPU上就能运行良好，那你就不用关心这个。
a single GPO, then you don't care about this.
这意味着这段代码路径不会被激活。
That means that this code pass is not going to be able to activate it.
但在很多情况下，就像今天的例子一样，
But in many cases, in today's case,
我认为一个GPU实际上无法在合理的时间内训练一个模型，所以你必须这样做。
I don't think a GPU can actually train a model in reasonable amount of time, so you have to do this.
你需要把这个计算图分布到很多很多设备上，
You're going to take this graph and going to distribute this graph over many many devices and
并且确保结果依然是正确的。
make sure the results are still correct.
明白了吗？然后我们还关心运行时的表现。
Okay? And then we also care about the run time.
也就是说，一旦运行了，它会消耗多少内存，应该如何运行。
That is once it runs, how many memory consume, how it should run.
有这么多操作符，对吧。
There are so many operators, right.
有左分支，也有右分支。
There's a left branch, there's a right branch.
我应该如何安排每个分支的调度？
How should I schedule each branch?
是不是应该让一个分支提前运行，还是应该延迟一个分支优先另一个分支。
Should one branch run ahead of time, or should delay the schon one branch over the other.
这很重要，因为它基本上会影响你的效率，是的。
And this matters because it can basically affect your efficiency, yeah.
我们也会讨论这个问题。
And we're going to talk about this as well.
最后，在Louis层，请记住，这些图是由许多
And finally, at the Louis layer, remember, these graphs are constructed by a lot of
原语构建的，这些原语可以是Mm、softmax等。
primitives and the primitives could be Mm, softmax and whatever.
最终，如果你想运行这个图，你需要运行这些原语。
Eventually, if you want to run this graph, you need to run those primitives.
这意味着你必须提供一个原语库，
That means that you have to provide a library of primitives that can
能够在不同类型的设备上运行，比如GPU、CPU等。
run on different kind of devices like GPU CPU, whatever.
在更底层，我们基本上有算子库，在那里我们实现了这些算子的实现，
Lower layer, we basically have operator library where we implement the implementation,
也就是我们所说的这些算子、原语在目标设备上的内核。
the exact we call kernels of these operators, primitives on those target devices.
这是非常底层的代码，我们也会涉及到这一部分。
This is a pretty low level code, and we are also going to touch base on that.
这基本上可以让你了解流程和影响方面的整体情况。
This basically gives you an overview of what's going on in terms of flow and impacts.
呃，这根本行不通。
Uh, it is simply not working.
但如果你去看TenderfowKolbs或Patrick obises，你会发现有比这更多的层次。
But if you go to TenderfowKolbs or Patrick obises you'll find there are much more layers than this.
但基本上，你可以把好几层合并成其中一层。
But basically, you can condense several layers into one of these.
明白了吗？有问题吗？
Okay? Any question?
好的。那我简单介绍一下每一层主要在做什么。
Cool. Okay, let me give you overview basically what each layer is cooking.
所以，如果你想在这个领域做研究，
So basically, if you want to do research in this,
你其实可以选择你最感兴趣的那一层。
you can actually choose a layer that is most interesting.
我可以告诉你，每一层实际上都已经有一千多篇论文发表了。
And I can tell you each layer actually has already more than 1,000 papers published.
讨论如何进行操作。
Discussing how to do openation.
嗯。
Yeah.
好的。第一层，正如之前所说，是图操作。
Okay. The first layer, graph openation as already said,
其目标基本上是将用户定义的原始图G重写为
the goal is basically rewrite the original graph G, defined by users into
另一个图，称为G prime。
another graph, which is called G prime.
我的目标是让G prime的运行速度比G快得多。明白吗？
And my goal is G prime will run much faster than G. Okay?
你可能会好奇为什么会这样。
You probably are wondering why this could happen.
我会给你举个例子，看看左边这部分图，对吧？
I'm going to give you an example and look at the left piece of graph, right?
那你能猜出这是来自哪里吗？
So can you guess where is this from?
很明显，这里有一个count到D，所以一定来自卷积网络。
Apparently, there's a count to D, so it must from convolutional network.
更准确地说，是来自resnet。
And to be more precise, is from resent. Okay.
在餐厅里，你基本上有输入X。
And in restaurant, you basically have input X.
你需要等待W和B。
You have to wait W and B.
你首先应用一个计数二，对吧？
You first apply a count two, right?
一旦你得到输出，你就会得到输出Y，
And once you get the output, you are going to get the output Y,
然后你还有另外两个参数R和P，你运行一个bachelor，然后得到第二个O Z。
and you have another two parameters R and P, and you run a bachelor and you get the second O Z.
为了稍微简化一点，我们基本上可以在这里表示交换，对吧？
And to simplify a little bit, we can basically represent the commutation there, right?
所以第一层基本上是计数二，就是一些循环和求和，对吧？
So the first layer is basically count two, which is some loops and sums, right?
然后加上偏置B。
And then plus bias B.
第二层基本上是取第一层的输出Y，然后做别的事情。
And the second layer is basically take the output of the first layer of Y and do something else.
好吗？这是这个图的简化版本。
Okay? This is a simplified version of this graph.
有一种方法可以让这个过程更快，就是我们不运行这个计算图，而是这样做。
And one way we can make this faster is we don't run this graph, but we do this.
我们发现其实可以把这个计算展开一点，
We find that we can actually enroll this computation a little bit,
我们尝试定义一些其他的方式，叫做W二和B二，
we try to define some other ways called W two and B two,
其中W二和B二的定义就在这里。
where the definition of W and B two is there.
那我们具体做了什么呢？我们在图层面提前进行了一些计算。
What do we do oicly we perform some computation ahead of time, on the graph level.
我们把W二定义为原始的W乘以R，也就是权重，
We define W two as the original width W times the R which is the weight
batm的权重，B二也是类似的。
of the batm and similarly for B two.
这样我们就不需要再运行batom了。
And then we don't have to run batom.
对，我们把所有的计算都合并到一个计数为二的操作符里，但实际上
Right, we field all the computation into one operator with count two, but we behind the scene
我们只是把权重从W和B切换成了w2和b。
we basically switch the weight from W B into w2b.
事实证明，第二个计算图运行速度比第一个快得多，对吧？
And it turns out that the second graph runs much faster than the first one, right?
这很明显，因为你总是多运行了一个算子，对吗？
Because it's quite obvious because you alwayd running one more operator, ok?
嗯，我们可以更激进地进行优化。
Um, and we can do it more aggressively.
我们的方法是整体观察数据流图的重复部分。
The way we do it is we are going to look at the holistic repetition of the dataflow graph.
我们会寻找每一个可以把C、D和Bachelom合并的机会。
We are going to look for every opportunity that we can put C D and Bachelom together.
在这里，我要给你一个非常极端的例子。
In this one, I'm going to give you a very extreme example.
这里有输入，我们先经过两个卷积操作，也就是1x1卷积，
Here we have input. We are going through two convolution, which is one by one convolution,
然后我们经过C的3x3卷积，再把结果相加，
then we go through C three by three and then add the results together and
再经过激活函数，得到最终结果。
go through value and get the results.
很明显，这里的1x1和3x3卷积，它们的滤波器大小是不同的。
And here, apparently, this one by one and three by three, their filter size are different.
一个是三乘三，另一个是一乘一。
One is three by three, the other one by one.
所以把它们合并成一个算子并不容易。
So it's not very easy to put them together into one operator.
那我们要做的就是把这个一乘一扩展成三乘三。
So what do we do is we are going to enlarge this one by one into a three by three.
我们可以这样做，对吧？从数学上来说是等价的，你可以这么做，
We can do that, right, mathematically equivalent, you can do that,
但问题是通过扩展操作，这个算子显然会变慢，
but the problem is through enlarging operation, this operator apparently will become
因为之前我们只需要计算一乘一，现在要计算三乘三了。明白吗？
slower because previously we only calculate one by one, but now we calculate three by three. Okay.
记住，这一步会变慢。
Remember, this step becomes lower.
但好处是，现在这个一乘一在形状上至少和三乘三等价了。
But the benefit is now this one by one becomes equivalent at least on shape with three batter.
我们可以把数学公式写在一起，然后把它们填充到三乘三里。
We can write the mathematical equation together and we can fill them into 13 battery.
好的，这一步会稍微快一点，对吧？
Okay. And this step is going to be slightly faster, right?
所以我们变慢了，然后又变快了。
So we become slower and then faster.
然后我们继续这样做。
And we continue doing this.
在这里，你可以看到，呃，我们将要把这些分裂的部分填充进来并全部
So here, you can see, uh, we are going to fill this split come and add all
合并成一个更完整的故事。
together into a more complete sstry.
如果你比较这个图和这个图，你会发现我们减少了
And if you compare this graph and this graph, you'll find that we reduce
从这个图到这个图的节点数量。
the number of nodes from this graph to this graph.
比如这个图只有两个节点，而这个图有很多节点。
Like this graph only have two nodes, but this graph has so many nodes.
我们可以继续填充，最终我们把整个图填充成只有两个节点。
And we can continue to fill and eventually we fill the autograph into into one, only two nodes.
好的，你可以看到，这很有趣，因为我们
Okay. You can see, this is pretty interesting because we
首先让图变慢，然后又让它变快了。
first make the graph slower and then we make it faster.
如果你评估这个优化后的计算图，你会发现它比原始的计算图更快。
And if you evalue the vital graph, you'll find as as the vital graph is faster
只要优化后的计算图比第一个计算图更快，我们就达到了目标。
than the first graph, we are good.
明白了吗？这基本上就是我们对计算图进行增强的方法。
Okay? This is basically what we do for graph augmentation.
而且考虑到我们的计算图有成千上万个节点，还有很多不同的操作符，
And given that our graph has thousands of nodes and there are so many different operators,
你可以想象我们有很多机会进行这种增强，对吧？
you can imagine there are so many opportunities that we can do this kind of augmentation, right?
这就是大家在这一层要做的事情。
And that's what people do in this layer.
好的。我记得在最初的课程，尤其是上周的课程，有些同学，
Okay. Um, I think in the initial lecture, especially in last week's lecture, some people,
有学生问我为什么融合操作会比原始计算图更快？
some students ask me why fusing can be faster than the original graph?
我们来深入探讨一下。但在此之前，我们先看一个更实际的例子。
Let's do a deep dive. But before that, let's look at a more realistic example.
这个你们应该很熟悉。
This is familiar.
这是注意力机制中的transformer注意力，对吧？
This is attention transformers attention, right?
如果你还记得注意力机制，我们要做的是用meto来操作
And if you still remember in attention, what we do is we are going to play with meto that
就是我们有QK的权重w，还有输入，也就是边的隐藏向量，
is we have weight for QK w and we have input, which is the edge hidden vector,
然后我们要把它们和大写的QQ一起组合在一起，
and we are going to me met mood them together together the capital QQ,
接着我们要执行注意力操作。
then we are going to perform attention.
但如果你去看任何一个transformer库，你会发现他们并不是这样写的
But if you go into any transformer library you will find that they don't write
他们不会用这种数学方式或者程序方式来实现。
mathematical or programs in this way.
他们会这样写，就是，
They are going to write in this way, that is, uh,
他们会把QQw合并，然后直接在一个输出中计算QQv
they are going to merge the QQw and then they directly calculate the QQv in one output
这个输出变量被称为QQvO。
which is called QQvO thing variable.
显然这就是融合。
Apparently this is fusion.
我们基本上是在通过融合一些算子来减少计算图的规模。
We are basically, reducing the graph size by fusing some operators.
好的，那回到刚才的问题。
Okay then back to the question.
为什么这样会更快？是什么根本机制让它变得更快？
Why this could be faster? What is the fundamental mechanism that makes this faster?
记住，在计算中我们关心的是算术强度，通常用AI表示，
So remember that in computing, we care about arismtic intensity, which is denoted as AI,
另一个AI，算术强度，它被定义为执行的数学操作数量，
another AI, arithmetic intensity, this is defined as the lumber mathematical operations,
呃，比如计算操作，除以，呃，内存访问的次数，
uh, like compute operations, divided by, uh, the lumber memory access,
就是你要从内存或其他存储设备读取多少比特数据。
like how many bits you are going to rate from your memory or whatever kind of storage.
明白了吗？这个值越高，就意味着你能更好地利用计算硬件，
Okay? And the higher this value, then that means you can utilize your computer hardware better,
这就会转化为更快的计算速度。
and that will translate into faster competition.
好的。呃，这种融合之所以有效，是因为如果你看这个例子，
Okay. Uh, the reason that this fusion works because if you look at this example,
我们基本上要做的是有两个浮点数组A和B。
what we do is basically we have to array flowing point rage A and B.
我们尝试把它们的值相加，然后把结果放到
We try to add their values and throw the value into
C中。这是一个非常简单的例子，但它有助于我们理解AI，也就是原始强度。
C. And this is a very simple example, but it helps us understand AI, okay, original intensity.
我们实现的方法是用循环，对吧？
So the way we do that is we rate loop, right?
我们遍历数组，然后把结果写入
We look through the rays and we write the result into
C中，我们可以估算结果的强度。
C. And we can estimate the resin intensity.
在这个过程中，我们首先读取A[i]，对吧？
So in this process, we first read AI right.
这是一次读取，然后我们读取B[i]，把它们相加。
This is one ad, then we read BI and we add them together.
这是一次计算机操作。
This is a computer operation.
然后，一旦我们有了结果，我们就把结果放到C里。
And then once we have the results, we throw the result into C. So
那么有多少是像计算机一样的操作，有多少是读写操作。
how many like a computer and how many read and write.
所以是一个计算操作，对吧，然后有三个读写操作。
So one computer, right, and three ran rate.
所以AI本质上就是，嗯，一除以三，对吧？好的，一比三。
So the AI is essentially, um, one divide by three, right? Okay, one by three.
如果我们继续这样做，写出更复杂的算法，也是同样的道理。
Same thing if we continue doing this, we make more complicated algorithm and written in this way.
也就是说，我们尝试把所有结果加在一起，然后把结果存到E里。呃，
That is, we try to add all the results together and store result in E. Uh,
抱歉，我们尝试把A和B加起来，再加上C和D，然后把结果放到E里。我们
sorry, we try to add A and B and T C and plus D and throw result in E. And what we
做的基本上是先把A和B相加，把结果存到临时变量里。
do is basically we first add A and B, strew results in temp.
然后我们按照这个顺序继续计算，直到得到我们想要的最终结果。
Then we follow this order and continue to compute until we get the final results we want.
那么，这个程序的AI是多少？
And so what is the AI of this program?
这也是三分之一，对吧，因为这条线是三分之一。这条线是三分之一。
It's also one by three, right, because this line is one by three. This line is one by three.
这个模块也是三分之一，因为我们读取了临时变量一，
And this mall is also one by three because we read temp one,
C，并把结果写入临时变量二。
C and write results into temp two.
这个也是三分之一。
And this one is also one by three.
所以总的来说，还是三分之一。
So in total, it's still one by three.
好的，好的。但如果我们稍微把这个程序写得
Okay. Okay. But if we slightly write this program in
更高效一点，我们就能得到这个程序。
a more efficient way that is we can get this program.
我不是一步一步地计算结果。
Instead of I calculate the results step by step.
我基本上是在一个长公式里计算。
I basically calculate in a long equation.
我要读取A、B、C和D，然后直接一起进行一些运算，
I'm going to read A, B, C, and D. I directly perform some competition altogether,
然后我把它扔到E里，这个的AI是多少？
and then I throw it out into E, what is the AI over this one?
所以我们可以看到有一个速率。
So we can see there's one rate.
有一个速率，对吧，先读A，第二条路B，第三，第一根棒D，第五写E。
There's one rate, right, read A, second road B, third, first rod D and the fifth write E.
所以IO基本上是五。
So the IO is basically five.
计算机这边是有一个加，一个加，还有一个乘。
And the computer is there's one plus, one plus, and one multiplier.
所以计算机这边是。
So the computer is.
所以AI本质上是三比五。
So the AI is essentially three by five.
我们可以看到这基本上是操作融合，对吧。
And we can see this is basically opera fusion right.
因为如果你把这个程序映射到计算图上，这里只有一个节点
Because if you map this program into computer graph, this one only have one node
它基本上把所有东西都连接在一起。
that basically connect everything together.
但是这个有很多节点会写入和读取结果。
But this one has so many nodes that will write and read results.
所以如果你做这种融合，你会发现你的AI会高很多。
So if you do this kind of o fusion, you will find out your AI is much higher.
这就是为什么我们真的希望尽可能多地进行融合。
That's why we really want fuse as much as possible.
明白了吗？我们大概在两节课之后会回到这个话题，然后我们会讨论
Okay? And we're going to go back to this in probably two lectures away, and we are going to talk
如何找到这些机会。
about how we can find these opportunities.
好的。正如我所说，为了执行这种图优化，有很多方法。
Okay. As I said, in order to perform this kind of graph ormentation, there are many ways.
一种方法是你可以写很多很多规则。
One way is you can write many many rules.
比如说，你可以在图上写一个扫描器，这个扫描器程序会
For example, you can write a scanner on the graph, and that scanner program will
基本上检查你的模板。
basically uh check your templates.
只要我发现有一个com操作符和另一个com操作符连接在一起，
As long as I find there's a com operator connected with another con operator,
我将要应用一种特定的融合方法。
I'm going to apply a specific fusion.
这是目前最常用的融合技术。
This is the most adopted, uh, fusing technique.
如果你查看TensorFlow的代码，他们有很多模板都是用这种方式写的。
And if you check tender flow code, uh, they have so many templates that are written in this way.
他们有一个图扫描器，会扫描计算图，基本上就是寻找优化的机会。
Okay? They have a graph scanner will scan the graph that basically find opportunities.
另一种方式是一些前沿研究，人们发现
Another way is some cutting research where people find that
有一些自动化机制可以发现这种融合技术，
there are some automatic mechanism that we can discover this kind of fiting techniques,
我们稍后会再详细介绍。
and we'll cover a little bit later.
这给你一个关于图优化整体情况的概览。
Okay. This gives you an overview of what's going on on the graph oppoiation.
希望你觉得有趣，有什么问题吗？
I hope it's interesting. Any question?
好的，那我们再深入一层来讲解。
Okay. Then let's go to one layer deeper.
一旦我们打开这个图，我们希望将这个图部署到许多设备上，
Once we open this graph, we want to deploy this graph over many,
这就叫做并行化。
many devices, that is called paralyzation.
并行化的问题在于我有一个计算图，还有一些设备集群。
And the problem paralyzation is that I have a computer graph, and I have some device cluster.
这个可视化让你看到媒体中正在发生什么，
And this visualization gives you a picture of what's going on in media,
媒体基本上以某种集群的形式塑造它，就像Google开放Amado一样。
media basically shapes it kind of cluster to Google opening Amado.
我想通过这个可视化强调的关键点是，
The key point I want to make through this visualization,
你可以看到，vida通常会以这种方式构建集群。
you can see, vida usually make this cluster in this way.
也就是说，它有很多很多节点，每个节点有几个GPU，通常是八个或四个。
That is, it has many many nodes, and each node has a few GPUs, typically eight or four.
在每个节点内部，这些GPU通过一种叫做
And inside of each node, uh, those GPUs are connected using communication technology called
veilink的通信技术连接，veilink的速度非常快，几乎和直接从内存读取一样快。
veilink that unveiling super fast is almost as fast as reading things directly from memory.
好吗？但是如果两个位于不同节点的GPU想要通信，
Okay? But if any two GPUs located on two different nodes wants to communicate,
它们是通过其他互连方式连接的。
they are connected using some other interconnect.
比如说，InfiniBand或者其他什么。
For example, infinite band or whatever.
那个不是由NVIDIA制造的，是其他公司生产的。
That one was not manufactured by media by someone else.
那个连接的速度比NVLink慢十倍，甚至一百倍。
That one is ten times slower or even 100 times slower than the link.
所以如果你想把这个图分布到这些节点上，你必须考虑到这一点，
So if you want to distribute this graph over this, you have to take this into
因为这是NVIDIA给我们的硬件条件。
consideration because this is what media giving to us.
你必须找到一种方法来切分这个图，把每一部分放到不同的设备上。
You have to find a way to cut this graph and put every part of it on different devices.
这样一部分通信会发生在节点内部，另一部分通信会发生在节点之间。
So some communication will happen inside node, and some communication will happen across nodes.
那么一般来说，什么样的通信应该发生在节点内部呢？
So in general, what kind of communication should happen inside of node,
以及节点之间应该进行什么样的通信。
and what kind of communication should happen across nodes.
正如我所说，在一个节点内部，你没有带宽限制，通信速度非常快。
As I said, inside of a node, you have not bandoes you communicate pretty fast.
所以你可以把大量的通信放在节点内部。
So you can put heavy communication inside node.
但在节点之间，你有一些较慢的互连。
But across nodes, you have some snow interconnect.
所以你要确保你的布局方式能够最小化节点之间的通信。
So you want to make sure you place in a way where you minimize the communication between nodes.
明白了吗？这基本上就是我们要解决的问题。
Okay? That is basically what pi trying to solve.
所以当我们尝试切分这个图时，我们是在寻找一种能够最小化节点间通信的方法，
So when we try to cut this graph, we try to find a way that minimize communication across nodes and
并最大化节点内部的通信。
maximize communication between nodes.
对吧？你可以看到这又变成了另一个优化问题。
Yeah. Okay? You can see this boils down into another opimenting problem.
并且根据通信模式，我们会在其上应用不同的算法。
And depending on the communication pattern, we are going to put different algorithm on top of it.
这也是训练大规模模型所必需的关键部分。
And this is also the essential part needed for training models at large as
GBD，我们稍后会深入讲解这个内容，好吗？关于这一层有问题吗？
GBD and we are going to do a deep dive on this later, okay? Any questions on this layer?
也许我可以用更像Groni的语言来讲，好吗？
Yeah, maybe I can speak more like Groni language, okay?
你们可能听说过张量并行之类的东西，对吧？
You probably heard about things like tensor paralism, right?
还有流水线并行、序列并行、上下文并行。
Pipeline palism, sequence paralism, context paralism.
它们基本上都是在尝试找到一种方法，
They are basically trying to figure out a way that basically
来解决我刚才提到的那个问题，好吗？
solve that problem I just mentioned, okay?
我们会涵盖所有这些内容。
And we are going to cover all this.
就像我说的，你需要弄清楚如何构建图、如何通信，
Like I said, you want to figure out how to graph, how to communicate,
因为现在你有了通信计算机，所以你需要安排通信计算机的调度。
because now you have communicated computer, so you want to schedule the communicate computer
所以它们尽可能多地重叠，呃，因为你在做分布式通信，
so they overlap as much as possible, uh, because you are doing distributed communication,
所以你关心一致性，你想确保分布式
so you care about consistency, you want to make sure distributed
和非分布式的结果是一样的，有时候你希望自动
versus non distributed the results are the same, sometimes you want to automatically
并行化，因为你要开发新的神经网络
paralyze it because you are going to develop new neur networks
而你不想关心，也不想为每个新写的网络
and you don't want to care about you don't want to craft paralyzing strategy
手动设计并行化策略。
for ach new network you wrote.
好的，然后我们进入另一个层面，对吧，就是运行时和调度。
Okay and then we go to another layer behind, right, runtime and scheduling.
所以在这一层，我觉得很直接，对吧？
So in this layer, I think it's pretty straightforward, right?
就是我们在操作系统里做什么，怎么让程序运行起来。
It's what do we do in operating systems, how we make a program run.
所以我们基本上想要以某种方式调度计算、通信和内存，基本上，
So we basically want to schedule the computer and communication and memory in a way that basically,
首先，你需要足够快。
first, you need to be fast.
其次，我们希望通信和计算能够重叠进行。
Second, we want to overlap the communication and compute.
第三，我们的内存不是无限的。
And third, our memory is not infinite.
我们只有80G的A或H100，所以我们需要受到内存限制的约束。
We have 80 giga for A or H 100, so we want to be subject to the memory constraints.
明白吗？这基本上就是运行时要做的事情。
Okay? That is basically what runtime does.
嗯，所以呢？
Yeah. So what?
呃，这是个很好的问题。
Uh that's a great question.
没有人对此加以限制。这也是为什么现在有很多创业公司在做芯片。
No one is limiting that. That's why there are many many startups building silicons, today.
他们正在筹集大量资金。
And they are raising a lot of money.
他们基本上是在尝试从媒体中构建不同的配置。
And they are basically trying to build different configurations from media.
比如说，英伟达给你配备了80G的显存，
For example, media, give you a memory of 80 giga,
而AMD基本上给你配备了160G的显存。
and AMD is basically giving you a memory of 160 giga.
最终，这还是取决于你的工作负载。
Eventually, it depends on your workload.
你的工作负载可能只需要80G，所以你没必要多花钱
Your workload probably only need 80 giga, so you don't have to pay extra price
去买160G的显卡。
to buy the 160 giga cards.
是的，现在有很多半导体公司在制造各种不同类型的硬件，
Yeah. So there are so many uh silicon companies are building different kind of hardware,
我们稍后会聊一下这个话题。
we are going to talk about that a little bit.
也许下一个话题再说，好吗？
Maybe next next, okay.
最后，我们来看更底层的内容，我们要讨论如何实现一个非常非常，
And finally, we go to the layer below, we are going to talk about how to implement a really, really,
非常快的基础操作，特别是针对metamo。
really fast primitive, especially for metamo.
就像我说的，如果你解决了metamo，你就解决了80%的问题。
Like I said, if you solve metamo you solve 80% of the problem.
但事情并没有那么简单，因为当你谈到算子实现时，
Um but it's not that simple because when you talk about operator implementation,
你会遇到很多多样性的问题。
you face a lot of diversity issues.
首先，你有不同的硬件架构，就像你提到的那样，
That is first you have different hardware architecture like that you mentioned,
你需要针对不同代的MDA GPU进行优化，BD每两年都会推出新GPU，
you need to optimize for different generations of MDA GPUs BD will ship GPUS every two years,
你甚至还有TPU、CPU，比如说，
you also even have TPU CPU and for example,
M三、M四之类的东西。
M three, four, this kind of things.
你希望你的程序能在所有地方运行。
You want your to run on everywhere.
你必须为每一个硬件平台定制算子实现。
You have to craft operator imitations for every hardware platform.
第二，你还有不同的方式来存储这些张量值。
Eight. Second, you have different ways of storing these tensor values.
你可以用不同的精度来存储它。
You can store it in different precisions.
对于每种精度，设备会使用不同的曲线。
For each precision, it will use different curves from the device.
所以程序也会不同。
So the program will be different.
因此你必须为每种精度设计不同的内核。
So you have to craft a different kernel for each precision.
正如你可能知道的，媒体一直在大力倡导降低精度。
As you probably know, media is strongly advocating for reducing precisions.
就像十年前，我们还在用32位精度训练神经网络。
Like ten years ago, we are training neural network on 32 bits of precisions.
而现在，如果你看看最新的神经网络，它们都是用16位精度训练的，直到今年，
And today, if you check the latest neural network, they are trained on 16 up to this year,
最先进的AM基本上是用FP8训练的。
the std art AM is basically trained on FP eight.
Jensen在圣诞节发布了一张新卡，他说，现在你可以用FP4来训练。
Jensen who give a new card during Christmas, he said, no, you can train on FP four.
也就是说，每个权重基本上只用四个位来表示。
That is each weight is basically represent using only four bits.
这怎么可能呢？
How could that be possible?
我们接下来会深入探讨这个问题。
And we are going to dive into that.
第三个问题基本上是，记住，我们的操作符有不同的形状。
The third issue is basically, remember, our operators have different shapes.
我们可能会有3x3的，也可能会有5x5的。
We could have three by three come, we could have five by five come.
对于MTM来说，我们可能会有2D和3D的。
And for MTM, we could have 2d3d.
由于我们存储数值的方式，同一种操作在不同形状下
And because of this because of the way we store the values, um, uh, a a same kind of probably
可能会有非常不同的性能表现，我们也会深入讨论这个问题。
will have very different performance on different shapes, and we are going to dive into that.
有时候我们会针对某些特定的形状进行索引。
And sometimes we index on some specific shapes.
就像我刚才说的，比如对于count 2D，我们非常关注X的性能
As I said, for example, for count two D, we really care about the performance of X
因为它是ret net的基石，对吧。
because it is a cornerstone of ret net, right.
对于这个met Mo，呃，
And for this met Mo, uh,
2d3d，我们非常关注某些值，某些是2的幂次方的维度，因为
2d3d, we really care about some value, some dimensions of power two because it
这是人们构建transformers和TPD的方式，我们想为他们做到极致优化。
is the way how people build transformers and TPD, and we want to optimize to the extreme for them.
好的。这些因素基本上让
Okay. And all these factors basically make the implementation of
算子的实现变得非常非常复杂。
operators really, really complicated.
好吗？好的，有了这些，
Okay? Okay. With that,
我觉得我基本上给你们概述了一下现在机器学习系统的人们
I think I basically, give you an overview of what merchant learning system people are
在做什么，以及大家在petro和tender flow里都在“烹饪”些什么。好吗？
doing and what basically people are cooking in petro and tender flow. Okay?
让我们回到我们的整体框架图。
Let's go back to our high level picture.
所以现在我们知道如何表示我们的模型了，对吧？数据流图。
So now we know how to represent our models, right dataflow graph.
我们也知道如何基本表示我们的反向传播过程，好吗，关于反向传播。
We also know how to basically represent our backward pass, okay, for backward pass.
嗯，我们接下来会讲一下如何表示数据，
Um, we are going to talk about how to represent data a little bit,
但一般来说，数据是用张量来表示的，对吧？
but in general, data is represented using tensors, right?
但是张量里面有一些神奇的地方，我们也会讲到。
But there are some magics in tensors, we are going to talk about that.
记住，我们的最终目标是把这些数据和模型表示，
And remember, our ultimate goal is we take this data and this mode representation,
在不同的硬件上实现高效运行，好吗？有问题吗？
we are going to make it fast on different hardware, okay? Any question?
好的，太好了。我觉得这基本上就把基础内容讲完了。
Okay, cool. I think that basically wrap up the basics.
那我们接下来进入第一层，我们会从
Then let's basically go into the first layer, and we are going to start from
运算符优化层开始讲起。
the operator optimization layer.
好的，我们要讲讲如何真正实现一些高效的运算符。
Okay, we are going to talk about how to really implement some fast operators.
所以记住我们的目标，针对这里这种操作符，我给你一个元操作。
So remember our goal, given this kind of operator here, I give you a meto.
我们的目标是尝试找到在CPNTP上非常非常快的实现，从这里开始构建，
Our goal is try to find implementation that is very, very fast on CPNTP building from there,
我们将要组合越来越复杂的数据流图。
we are going to compose more and more complicated data phlograph.
嗯，我想我已经说过了，我再重复一遍。
Um, I think I already said that and I repeat.
这一层的目标是，我们试图找到能够最大化AI的实现，好吗？
The goal of this layer is we try to find implementation that is well that will maximize AI, okay?
我们基本上是想让计算量尽可能多。
We try to basically make the number of compute as much as possible.
但我们要尽量减少内存IO的访问。
But we try to minimize the memory IO access.
这基本上就是计算的基本原理，对吧？
That is basically the fundamentals of compute, right?
我们要最大化原始强度。
We try to maximize the original intensity.
在这一部分，我们要讨论三件事，对吧。
In this part, we are going to talk about three things, right.
首先是图像学习，我们如何让算子整体变得更快，
First is the image learning, how we can make the operator fast in general,
不管是什么平台，比如说无论你用的是CPU还是GPU，
regardless of platforms, for example, no matter you are using CPO or GPU,
我们要怎么让算子变快。
how we can make operator fast.
然后，正如我刚才说的，MTMo非常重要，所以我们要深入探讨MT MO。
Then, as I said, MTMo is so important, so we are going to dive into MT MO.
我们会进行非常深入的讲解。
We're going to very deep dive.
接着，因为GPU是目前主要的计算平台，
And then because GPU is a major platform for computing today,
是一种特殊的硬件，所以我们会深入讲解如何让这些算子在GPU上变快。
is special machinery, so we are going to dive deep into how to make this operators fast on GPUs.
好的，那我们从第一个开始。
Okay, so let's start with the first one.
那么我们如何让算子整体变快呢？
So how we can make operator fast in general, okay?
通常来说，有三种方法可以让算子变快。
In general, there are three ways to make operator fast.
首先我们尝试对我们的操作符进行向量化，对吧？
The first ways we try to vectorize our operators, right?
如果你每天都写Lump Pi操作符，这其实很简单，对吧？
And this is pretty straightforward if you write Lump Pi operators every day, right?
写向量化代码总是比写面向对象编程要快。
Uh, writing vectorized code is always faster than writing a oop.
第二种方法是我们尝试调整数据布局。
The second way is we try to play with data layout.
通过定义合适的数据布局，也就是如何表示数据，
And by defining the right data layout, that is representing the data,
以正确的方式组织张量，我们实际上可以减少
inspite tensors in the right way, we can actually reduce overhead
许多机器学习操作符中的开销。
in many many operators in machinery.
第三种方式，当然，就是增加线程数并进行并行计算。
The third way, of course, per addition, we just give it more threats and we compute in parallel.
好吗？我们从第一个方法开始。
Okay? Let's start with the first one.
就像我说的，第一个方法其实很简单。
Like I said, the first one is pretty straightforward.
这是一段代码，我们在这里将A和B的值清除，并将结果写回到C中。
And this is a piece of code where we add the values to erase A and B and write values back to C.
其中一个版本基本上是我们使用了非向量化的版本。
One version of it is basically we use unvectorized, uh, version.
我们只是遍历所有的值。
We just loop over all the values.
但我们也可以进行向量化处理。
And we can vectorize it.
我们进行向量化的方法，基本上是调用一些更高级的函数，
The way we corize basically we are going to call some more advanced functions,
这个函数叫做load flow four。
which is called load flow four.
在这种情况下，每次我们都会从内存中加载四个浮点数到一个寄存器中。
In this case, every time we are going to load four floats inside one from the memory.
然后我们将这四个浮点数相加，并把结果写入另一个目标内存地址，
And we are going to add the four flows together and the write value into another destination memory
这个内存地址存储着四个浮点数，也就是C，然后我们
address which store four flows, which is called C, and then we
存储这个值并移动指针。
store the value and we move the pointer.
这是一个写操作的版本。
And this is a write version.
好吗？有人能告诉我为什么这个版本比左边的快吗？有谁知道吗？
Okay? Can anyone tell me why the version is faster than the left one? Yeah.
是的。在许多现代硬件中，它们有这种加载流水线，允许你一次加载多个值。
Yeah. Yeah. In many modern hardware, they have this kind of load flow four that allows you to load,
这样你可以一次性加载很多数值。
many values in one pass.
这是硬件制造商提供的功能。
This is given by the hardware manufacturer.
所以如果你能利用这一点，你基本上可以用这种方式实现计算的向量化。
So if you are able to leverage this, you basically can vectorize your compute in this way.
这已经内置到petrogentensor flow中了。
This has been built into petrogentensor flow.
我认为只要你调用默认的API，并且尽量让你的代码尽可能向量化，
I think as long as you call the default API and you try to write your code in a way that
它就会以这种方式工作，好吗？
is as vectorized as much as possible is what work in this way, okay?
这是记录点。第二点是我们还会调整数据布局。
That is recordis. The second one is we also play with data layout.
还记得一开始我们讲到全局概念的时候，
Remember at the beginning at the global picture,
我说我们的输入imergiO数据沉浸基本上是以张量的形式存储的。
I said our input imergiO data immersion is basically stored in tensor.
那什么是张量？张量基本上就是一个高维数组，那么从根本上说，
But what is tensor? Tensor is basically a high dimensional array, fundamentally, how is high
高维数组是如何在内存中存储的呢？
dimision array stored in memory?
好的。从根本上讲，在内存中，我们并不会真的存储任何高维的东西。
Okay. Fundamentally, in memory, we're not going to store anything that is high dimensional.
我们只能以一维的方式存储数据，对吧？
We can only store things in one dimension, right?
所以我们会以顺序的方式存储数据。
So we store things in a sequential way.
明白了吗？也就是说在内存层面，我们其实没有张量的概念，这基本上就是
Okay? That is from a memory level, we don't have any tensor awareness, and this basically visualize
我们存储数值的方式的可视化。
the way that we store values.
我们基本上就是从左到右进行存储。
We basically store from the left to right.
例如，在这里，每个值在内存中基本上占用八个字节。
For example, here, each value basically takes eight bytes in memory.
我们表示张量的方式基本上有两种，通常我们会介绍两种方式，一种是行优先。
And the way we represent tensor is basically, uh, we usually introduce two ways, one is row major.
另一种是列优先。
The other is column major.
我觉得你们大家应该都非常熟悉这个。
And I think all of you guys should be very familiar with this.
在行优先中，我们基本上是先存储每一行，
In row major, we basically store each row first,
然后再存储第二行和第三行。
and then we start with the second row and the third row.
在列优先中，方式相反，这里以二维情况为例，
In column major, the other way, this is for the two dimensional case,
但你可以推广到很多很多维度。
but you can generalize into many many dimensions.
明白了吗？这里有一个可视化图。
Okay? And this is a visualization.
第一个红色的是行优先，第二个是列优先。
The first one red one is row major, the second one is column major.
好的。我们需要注意数据的布局，因为如果你看这个程序，
Okay. And we need to be aware of data layout because if you look at this program,
假设我们的数据是按行优先存储的，也就是说我们画一个零，
assuming that our data is stored in row major, that is we draw a zero,
从零一直到零减一，然后我们再从
zero all the way to zero minus one, and then we start from uh
A10开始，然后继续按照行优先的顺序。
A 10 and then, following the row major.
好的。那么你觉得这个程序好吗？
Okay. So do you think this program is good?
为什么？因为如果你注意的话，你会发现这个循环是
Why? Because if you pay attention you will find that the loop is
先在内层维度循环，然后再在外层维度循环。
written in a way that it first loops from the inside of dimension, and then outside of dimension.
这样会非常慢。
And this is going to be extremely slow.
为什么？是的，缓存是一个问题。
Why? Yeah, cache is one problem.
第二个问题是，每次你尝试循环时，你都需要移动指针数组。
Second is going to every time when you try to tu loop, you are going to move the pointers array
这样会引入一些额外的压力。
of stress that way introduce some overhead.
改进这个程序的一种方法是，我们尝试交换那两个循环，先循环I再循环J。
One way to improve this program is basically we try to swap those two loops we loop I and then J.
这其实很简单。
This is pretty straightforward.
好，现在我们知道数据存储在张量中，我要给你们一个选择题。
Okay. Now we know that our data is stored in tensor and I'm going to give you MCQ,
机器学习系统是以行优先还是列优先存储数据的？
Machine learning systems store data in row major or column major.
谁想回答？比如说Piro。
Who wants to answer? Like for example Piro.
好的，其实我可以告诉你，他们并不是以行优先或列优先的方式存储数据。
Yeah. Okay. Actually, I can tell you, um, they don't throw data in row major or column major.
他们采用了一种新的格式来存储数据，我接下来会介绍。
They throw data in a new format which I'm going to introduce.
这种格式叫做strted格式，好吗？
That is called strted format. Okay?
那么什么是strted格式呢？
So what is the strategy format?
这基本上是这节课的最后部分。
This is basically the last part of this class.
好吗？所以在strted格式中，你需要引入另外两个参数。
Okay? So in strted format, you introduce two more parameters, okay.
第一个参数叫做偏移量。
The first parameter is called offset.
也就是说，当你尝试从张量中索引值时，你首先要加上偏移量的值。
That is when you try to index value from a tensor, you first add offset value.
好吗？第二个参数叫做步幅，步幅也是一个张量，
Okay? The second, parameter is called stress, and the stress is also tensor
它的维度和原始张量相同。
with a dimension equal to the original tensor.
好的，就像我刚才说的，偏移量基本上表示张量相对于
Okay. So like I said, the offset basically means that the offset of the tensor relative to
底层存储的偏移，步幅，
the underlying storage, the stress,
基本上表示在张量的某个维度上移动一个单位时，
I basically indicates how many elements need to be skipped in memory to move when
内存中需要跳过多少个元素。
unit in the dimension of the tensor.
这意味着这里你有一个三维张量数组，索引值的方式基本上是这样的，
That means that here you have array three dimensional tensor, the way that index value is basically,
你取底层存储，然后首先尝试计算索引以及偏移量，
you take underlying storage and you first try to calculate index as well plus offset,
然后你将每个维度乘以步长，最终你会得到这个值。
and then you multiply each dimension by strett and eventually you'll get this value.
这被称为步长格式。
This is called strategy format.
这很简单吧？让我们用一个非常简单的问题结束这节课。
This is pretty straightforward? Let's end this lecture with a very simple question.
这两个可视化基本上展示了步长格式的含义。
These two visualization basically give you what it means by strategy format.
花5秒钟看一下这个。
Take 5 seconds to look at this.
好的，我们很容易理解。
Okay. We easy to understand.
让我问你两个问题。
Let me ask you two questions.
那么当我们有二维的时候，会是什么情况？
So what do we have when we have two dimensions.
那么当我们让stride 0等于1时，我们得到了什么？
So what do we have when we have the stress zero equal to one,
而stride 1等于shape 0时，这是什么？
and the stress one equal to a shape zero. What is this?
这是列主序，对吧？
This is a column major, right?
你可以看到我们可以用不同的stride值来表示行主序或列主序。
You can see we can use, uh, different values of stress to represent the row major or column major.
我们也可以做类似的事情，就是一旦我们把stride的第一个维度设为shape 1，
And we can do something similar that is once we set the first dimension of stress equal
stride的第二个维度设为1，那么我们就得到了行主序。
to shape one and the second dimension of stress equal to one, then we get to the row major.
好，你可以看到stride实际上提供了很大的灵活性。那么为什么它灵活呢？
Okay. You can see stress actually gives a lot of flexibility. So why is flexible?
最后一个问题，好吗？如果一个形状为1,2,3,4的张量被共享，
Last question, okay? If a tensor of shape one, two, three, four is shared,
它在内存中是按照行主序连续存储的。
it stored continuous in memory following row major.
那stride是多少？我们都知道stride肯定是一个四维数组。
So what is the stress? So we all know that stress is definitely a four dimensional array.
抱歉，数组是四个元素，对吗？
Sorry, array was four entries, right?
那到底什么是步长呢？
So what is exactly the stress?
如果你在非主导汽油中这样做的话，你会发现基本上，
So if you do this, um, in inter non pilot petrol, you will find that basically,
我们创建了一个有24个元素的数组，然后我们用一、二、三、四来分组，并且我们尝试
we create array with 24 elements, and we ship using one, two, three, four, and we try to put
把步长设为24、12、4和1。
stress on well find stress be 24, 12, four, and one.
这意味着，如果你试图在第一维上移动一个元素，也就是这个维度，
That means, if you try to move an element in the first dimension that is this dimension,
你需要跳过24个元素。
you need to skip 24 elements.
如果你试图按照这个维度移动元素，你需要跳过12个元素。
And if you try to move element following this dimension, you need to skip 12 elements.
好的，非常直观。
Okay. Pretty straightforward.
好的，我们之所以有步长，是因为一旦我们有了这种存储元素的定义，
Okay. The reason we have stress is because once we have this kind of definition of storing elements,
实际上，我们可以利用这个线程来优化很多操作符，这部分我会在下节课讲解。
we can actually using this thread to optimize a lot of operators, which I will cover next lecture.
好的，今天就到这里，谢谢大家。
Okay. That's all I have today. Thank you.
嗯嗯。
H h.